Guide to the James Hamilton papers, 1769-1870, bulk 1785-1858 RL.00497
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Hamilton papers
1769-1870
1785-1858
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hamilton, James, 1763-1829
RL.00497
15 Linear Feet 16 boxes; 1 oversize folder Approximately 3700 items
Merchant and plantation owner of Charleston, S.C., later of Philadelphia, Pa. Collection comprises business and family correspondence, accounts, and receipts, including papers related to several of Hamilton's business partnerships (dating mainly from 1785 to 1818) and numerous private transactions, including purchases of slaves (1784-1785, 1801, 1808). There also are papers from voyages of ships in which he had a major interest, including routes to India, the Mediterranean, and the West Indies. The collection concludes with accounts and records related to the settlement of his estate from 1832 to 1870.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The James Hamilton papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in May 1976.
Biographical Note
James Hamilton (1763-1829) was likely born in Scotland, and emigrated to the United States in 1784. He established a business in Charleston, South Carolina, as a shipping merchant associated with Edward Mortimer & Co. of Charleston, David McCredie of Charleston and Savannah, and Henry Bethune & Co. of London. In 1800 he established a cotton plantation on St. Simons Island, Ga., with about 300 slaves, and later jointly owned (with John Couper) a second plantation property, a rice plantation with 450 slaves, Hopeton, on the Altamaha River near Darien, Georgia. He also acquired two substantial town homes, No.13 Broad Street in Charleston, and No. 260 Walnut Street in Philadelphia. His wife was Nancy Isabella Steedman (1780-c.1818) of London. They had two children, Agnes Rebecca, and George (b.1806).
At his death in April 1829 in Philadelphia, Hamilton owned four coastal Georgia plantations, and a total of 662 slaves, and was a very rich man. He devised his entire estate in trust to his grandchildren, of whom only one, Isabella Hamilton Corbin (b.1827), was alive in 1829. The other two legatees were Elizabeth T. Corbin (b.1831), and Richard Washington Corbin (1837-1922). Each heir was to receive a full one-third share upon reaching the age of 21 years. After his death the executors invested heavily in 5% bonds of the State of Pennsylvania, and during and after the Civil War in U.S. Treasury bonds. After the 1827 marriage of Agnes Rebecca Hamilton to Francis Porteus Corbin (1801-1876), a lawyer from Virginia, the Corbins lived in France. The other child, George, never married and later lived in Liverpool. Collateral relations included his wife's niece Isabella Bethune (1804), his wife's cousin Margerat (Mrs. Daniel) Kennedy (1805), his nephew Robert Wilson and grand-nephew James Hamilton Wilson, both of Liverpool, and his niece Janet Wilson of Philadelphia and Scotland.
In 1848, after two decades of the administration of Hamilton's estate, principally the Georgia slave plantations and the Pennsylvania state bonds and other financial investments, the estate was valuated at over $1 million, including 764 slaves.
As directed, from 1848-1858 the estate was successively divided among the three heirs, with Francis P. Corbin as trustee for the shares of Isabella H. (1848) and Elizabeth T. (1852), and with annuities funded principally by Pennsylvania and U.S. bonds exempted from the estate division, continuing to Agnes Corbin and George Hamilton through at least 1867.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises business and family correspondence, accounts, and receipts, including papers related to several of Hamilton's business partnerships (dating mainly from 1785 to 1818) and numerous private transactions, including purchases of slaves (1784-1785, 1801, 1808). There also are papers from voyages of ships in which he had a major interest, including routes to India, the Mediterranean, and the West Indies. The collection concludes with accounts and records related to the settlement of his estate from 1832 to 1870.
Merchant ships -- Records; Merchants -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Merchants -- South Carolina -- Charleston; Plantation owners -- Southern States; Slaveholders -- Georgia; Slaveholders -- South Carolina; Slavery -- Economic aspects; Slaves -- Southern States -- Economic conditions; Charleston (S.C.) -- Commerce -- History; Georgia -- History; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Commerce -- History; South Carolina -- History; Southern States -- History -- 1775-1865; Accounts; Hamilton, James, 1763-1829
- Correspondence, 1784-1892, 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Subject headings found in the correspondence were compiled by a researcher in 2005.
  - 1784-1892 (Box 1)
    Includes cotton and rice, London market, and shipping.
  - 1803-1805 Aug. (Box 2)
    Includes cotton and rice, London market, shipping, and one letter from niece in London, 1804.
  - 1805 Sept.-1806 Apr. (Box 3)
    Includes tobacco, steam engine (1805), cotton, financial, panic, France (1806), and politics.
  - 1806 May-1807 May (Box 4)
    Includes rice and tobacco.
  - 1807 June-1811 May (Box 5)
    Includes poor crops (1808) and other miscellaneous materials.
  - 1811 June-1811, 1853, 1892, and undated (Box 6)
- Business Papers, 3 boxes
  - Partnerships (Box 7)
  - Legal representation (Box 8)
  - Private transactions (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous accounts (Box 9)
- Financial Papers, 1 box
  - Bank checks and notes (Box 10)
- Commerce, 1 box
  - Commerce, 1796-1805 (Box 11)
- Trading Voyages, 1796-1818, 4 boxes; 1 oversize folder
  - Caroline, 1796-1797 (Box 11)
  - Charlotte, 1787-1788, 1812-1813 (Box 11)
  - Isabella, 1801-1805 (Box 12)
  - Isabella, 1806-1810 and undated (Box 13)
  - Savannah, 1805-1818 (Box 13)
  - Oversize trading voyages items (Oversize-folder 1)
- Estate Settlement, 1 box
  - Estate settlement, 1832-1870 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous, 2 boxes
  - Bills of exchange (Box 15)
  - Volumes (Box 15)
  - Receipts (Box 15)
  - Legal papers (Box 15)
  - Cartoon (Box 15)
  - Index cards (Box 16)